Paul Kammerer Papers 1910-1972 Mss.B.K128
American Philosophical Society
Paul Kammerer Papers, 1910-1972
Mss.B.K128
American Philosophical Society
0.25 Linear feet
The Austrian biologist Paul Kammerer was an outspoken proponent of the theory of inheritance of acquired characteristics (Lamarckism) during the time in which Mendelian theory was becoming deeply entrenched in biology. His major research efforts, straddling the First World War, centered on experiments performed on salamanders and on the midwife toad, and seemed to provide empirical support for a Lamarckian mechanism in evolution. He also developed a monistic "law of seriality," in which he attempted to explain coincidence as the product of a higher order natural law. A Socialist, Kammerer was widely regarded as a brilliant scientist, but for scientific, personal, and political reasons, he engendered as much antagonism as support, preventing him from ever obtaining a regular university appointment. His career ended tragically in allegations of fraud, followed by his suicide. The Kammerer Papers is comprised of photocopies of materials that document the brief, but controversial career of a non-Darwinian evolutionary biologist. The bulk of the collection consists of photocopies of articles by Kammerer, often from obscure newspapers or periodicals, along with a small number of letters to his friend Hugo Iltis, the geneticist and biographer of Mendel. Nearly all of these pertain to the Kammerer's experiments with amphibians to test Lamarckian inheritance or to his other biological theories. The collection also includes a small number of items dating from after Kammerer's death, but relating to his life and work, including two letters from his former supervisor Hans Przibram, a letter from Hugh Iltis (Hugo's son) to Arthur Koestler and the reply, and a brief biographical reminiscence of Kammerer written by Hugo Iltis.
Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926
Box 1
Bibliography
The APS owns copies of two of Kammerer's books:
Kammerer, Paul, Adaptation and Inheritance in the Light of Modern Experimental Investigation (Washington, 1913). Call no.: 506.73 Sm6an 1912
Kammerer, Paul, The Inheritance of Acquired Characteristics [transl. of Die Streitfrage der Vererbung erworbener Eigenschaften] (N.Y., 1924, 1984). Call no.: 575.1 R72h.r v.18
Genetics Note
This collection contains materials which relate to the history of genetics.
Dunn, Leslie Clarence -- Hugo Iltis - 1882-1952 Manuscripts (2 pages) 1953
Iltis, Hugo -- Curriculum Vitae Manuscripts (1 page) n.d.
Iltis, Hugo -- List of publications Manuscripts (3 pages) n.d.
Iltis, Hugo -- Paul Kammerer Manuscripts (1 item) Circa 1922
Iltis, Hugo -- Paul Kammerer Manuscripts (1 item) 1951
Kammerer, Paul -- Curriculum Vitae Manuscripts (1 item) 1910-1915
Kammerer, Paul -- Letters to Hugo Iltis Correspondence (6 items) 1910-1920
Related Archival Materials note
Kammerer appears as a correspondent in the Davenport (B D27) and Jennings (B J44) Papers at the APS.
Other Finding Aids note
The Kammerer Papers are discussed in Bentley Glass' Guide to Genetics Collections at the APS.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Hugh H. Iltis, Sept. 20, 1973 (accn. no. 1973-2035ms).
Scope and Contents note
The Kammerer Papers is comprised of photocopies of materials that document the brief, but controversial career of the non-Darwinian evolutionary biologist, Paul Kammerer. The bulk of the collection consists of photocopies of articles written by Kammerer, often from obscure newspapers or periodicals, along with a small number of letters from Kammerer to his friend Hugo Iltis, the geneticist and biographer of Mendel. Nearly all of these pertain to the Kammerer's experiments with amphibians to test Lamarckian inheritance or to his other biological theories. The collection also includes a small number of items dating from after Kammerer's death relating to Kammerer's life and work, including two letters from his former supervisor Hans Przibram, a letter from Hugh Iltis (Hugo's son) to Arthur Koestler and the reply, and a brief biographical reminiscence of Kammerer written by Hugo Iltis.
With the exception of some of the material dating from after Kammerer's death, the collection is written exclusively in German. Typescripts of Kammerer's letters have been included.
Biographical/Historical note
The Austrian biologist Paul Kammerer was an outspoken proponent of the theory of inheritance of acquired characteristics (Lamarckism) during the time in which Mendelian theory was becoming deeply entrenched in biology. Though widely regarded as a brilliant scientist, he engendered opposition for both personal and political reasons that prevented him from ever obtaining a regular university appointment, and his career ended tragically in allegations of fraud, followed by his suicide.
Born in Vienna in 1880, Kammerer received his doctorate from the University of Vienna in 1904, and was shortly thereafter appointed as assistant at the University's Biologische Versuchsanstalt, working under Hans Przibram. From that time until his death in 1926, Kammerer engaged in experiments on amphibians in an attempt to test the possibility of Lamarckian inheritance. In his earliest work, he took specimens of two species of salamander with markedly different environmental preferences, switched their habitats, and bred them in the foreign environment. The black-colored viviparous alpine salamander Salamandra alta was bred in a warm, aquatic, lowland environment, and the spotted oviparous lowland species Salamandra maculosa in a cold and dry environment. The results were striking. Kammerer reported that each type acquired the coloration of the other in its new habitat, and the acquired color patterns proved to be heritable. Furthermore, after a period of adjustment, Kammerer reported that S. alta became oviparous and vice-versa for S. maculosa.
Kammerer's next series of experiments were even more provocative. His idea was to test whether a change in environment like the one he induced in his salamander work would produce a similar phenotypic shift in the midwife toad ( Alytes obstetricians), a terrestrial species which lacks the pigmented "nuptial" thumb pads used by aquatic males to grasp females in mating. He concluded that the answer was yes: the environment could once again be shown to be a stimulus for the development of nuptial pads in the male, and these pads were inherited by male offspring even when returned to their original environment. Although Lamarckism had been widely accepted as an important evolutionary mechanism only a generation before, and although a number of recalcitrant Lamarckians still populated the field, Kammerer's empirical findings had a large impact, though much of it negative. In other work, he was no less controversial. An arch monist, he developed a "law of seriality," in which he attempted to explain coincidences or series of coincidences as manifestations of an underlying universal principle in nature that stands apart from physical causality.
While Kammerer's experiments were, in themselves theoretically challenging and controversial in the face of a solidifying Mendelism, they were made more so because of his political views and personality. A handsome man inclined to vanity and womanizing, Kammerer earned the envy and enmity of many. That he was a staunch Socialist, an atheist, and half Jewish on his mother's side, did little to help him in reactionary circles at the University, and his willingness to write for the popular press earned him the criticism of others who derided him as simply a journalist. His opponents prevented him from ever obtaining a proper university post, citing disapproval of his insistence on published Das Gesetz der Serie before obtaining the approval of the University Senate as reason. He spent most of his latter years as a Privat Dozent -- without pay.
Socialism may also have been one of the key elements behind Kammerer's receptivity to Lamarckian theory. Kammerer wrote that he saw evolution as the great hope that education could offer for the improvement of humanity, and his theories found a particularly appreciative audience among committed Socialists and Communists. The ideological coincidence earned Kammerer an invitation to join the faculty at Moscow University, an offer that the cultured and cosmopolitan native of Vienna did not immediately accept.
As news of his experiments began to spread in 1923, Kammerer left for a lecture tour of England, visiting Cambridge and the Linnaean Society in London, after which he traveled to the United States. As he lectured at universities from Yale to Johns Hopkins, Kammerer created something of a popular sensation, earning extravagant (and sometimes exaggerated) notice in the press for his ideas. In the scientific community, however, opinions ran the gamut from skepticism to denial: on the more positive end, Herbert Spencer Jennings remained open to the possibility of Lamarckian mechanisms, but at Cambridge, William Bateson sought actively to discredit him.
Kammerer's story diverted into tragedy in 1926 when G. Kingsley Noble of the American Museum and Przibram earned a rare invitation to visit Kammerer's laboratory in Vienna and examine his amphibians personally. During this visit, they discovered that the toad's nuptial pads had in fact been injected with India ink in order to produce the black coloration and swelling, and after they went to press with their accusations in the August 7, 1926, issue of Nature, the response was swift. Although Kammerer professed innocence, blaming an antagonistic assistant for the alteration, his reputation was sullied beyond repair. He accepted the position in a still-receptive Moscow, but Kammerer fell into a deep depression, suffering not only from the assaults on his character, but from poor finances and his wife's refusal to accompany him to Russia. He committed suicide en route to Russia. For almost three decades most, however, his work remained current in the Soviet Union, where his theories harmonized with the principles of Trofim Lysenko, head of the Institute of Genetics of the Soviet Academy of Sciences.
Dunn, L. C., (Leslie Clarence), 1893-1974; Iltis, Hugh H. (Hugh Hellmut); Iltis, Hugo, 1882-1952; Koestler, Arthur, 1905-1983; Przibram, Karl, 1878-1973; Adaptation (Biology); Amphibians; Evolution (Biology); Genetics--Austria; Heredity; Inheritance of acquired characters; Lamarckism
- Paul Kammerer Papers, 1910-1972; 0.25 lin. feet (Box 1)
  - to Hugo Iltis, 1910 July 6; ALS Cy, 2p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Please note that subject terms refer to all correspondence from Paul Kammerer to Hugo Iltis (6 items total). See below for the rest of the letters.
    Evolution; Genetics; Genetics -- Amphibians; Lamarck, Jean Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet de
  - to Hugo Iltis, 1910 July 9; ALS Cy, 1p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum vitae, ca.1910-1915; ALS Cy, 1p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
    Biographical and personal data
  - to Hugo Iltis, 1911 Dec. 28; Postcard Cy, 1p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
  - Mendelsche Regeln und Vererbung erworbener Eigenschaften, 1911; Pr. Ms Cy, 39p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
    Article from Verhanglungen des Naturforschenden Vereines in Brünn 49 (1911): 72-110.
  - Gefühl und Verstand, 1914 May; Pr. Ms Cy, 8p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
    Sonderdrücl from Monatsblätter der Deutschen onistenbundes Ortsgruppe Hamburg.
  - Zwei Janhre "Allgemeine Lebenslehre", 1914; Pr. Ms Cy, 15p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
    Article from Cottage-Lyzeum 1913/1914.
  - Erbliche Anlastung, 1916 ca. April 4; Pr. Ms Cy, 8p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
    Article from Wiener Urania on his experiments with salamanders.
  - to Hugo Iltis, 1919 Sept. 1; TLS Cy, 2p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
  - to Hugo Iltis, 1919 Dec. 19; TLS Cy, 2p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
  - Lebensbeherrschung: Grundsteinlegung zur organischen Technik, 1919; Pr. Ms. Cy, 2p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
    Published as Monistische Bibliothek 13 (1919).
  - Dunkeltiere im Licht und Lichttiere im Dunkel, 1920 Jan. 9; Pr. Ms. Cy, 8p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
    Published in Naturwissenschaften 13 (1920): 28-35.
  - to Hugo Iltis, 1920 Jan. 17; Postcard Cy, 2p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
  - Brief vom Wörtersee, 1920 Sept. 14; Pr. Ms. Cy, 1p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
    Published in Der Abend, p.3.
  - Richard Semon: zur Wiederkehr seines todestages, 1920 Dec. 27; Pr. Ms. Cy, 2p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
    Published in Der Abend, no.294.
  - Entwicklungsmechanik der Seele, 1920; Pr. Ms. Cy, 2p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
    Published in Der Freie Gendanke (Prague), 1, 7 (1920): 3.
  - Hilfreiche Entlastung, 1921 Jan. 26; Pr. Ms. Cy, 2p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
    Published in Der Abend.
  - Zufall, 1921 Mar. 16; Pr. Ms. Cy, 2p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
  - Der Kreislauf des Geschehens, 1921 July 3; Pr. Ms. Cy, 2p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
    Published in Berliner Tageblatt.
  - Welt-Widerhall Seele, 1921 July 5; Pr. Ms. Cy, 2p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
  - Jungbrunnen der Wissenschaft, ca.1921 July 10; Pr. Ms. Cy, 2p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
    Published in er Abend?.
  - Über Verjüngung und Verlängerung des persönlishen Lebens, 1921; Pr. Ms. Cy, pp.7-16 only; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
    Published in Stuttgart.
  - Zensur und Wissenschaft, ca.1921; Pr. Ms. Cy, 2p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
  - Paul Kammerer, ca.1922; Pr. Ms. Cy, 2p.; Iltis, Hugo (Box 1)
    Published in unknown source.
    Biographical and personal data -- Kammerer, Paul; Publication
  - to Hugo Iltis, 1923 July 23; ANS Cy, 1p.; Przibram, Hans, 1874- (Box 1)
    On Lamarckian evolution.
  - Dr. Kammerer und die Wiener Universität, ca.1924; Pr. Ms. Cy, 1p.; Molish, Hans(?) (Box 1)
    Published in Neue Freie Presse (Wien).
  - Notices on Kammerer's death, 1926; Pr. Ms. Cy, 4p. (Box 1)
  - to Hugo Iltis, 1930 Feb. 9; ALS Cy, 3p.; Przibram, Hans, 1874- (Box 1)
  - Die Abstammung Gregor Mendels, Julius Wiesners und Hans Molischs, ca.1938; Pr. Ms. Cy, 5p.; Iltis, Hugo (Box 1)
    Published in Prager Rundschau 8 (1938): 299-304.
  - Paul Kammerer, 1951; Pr. Ms. Cy, 4p.; Iltis, Hugo (Box 1)
    Dictated to Hugh H. Iltis.
    Biographical and personal data -- Kammerer, Paul; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Hugo Iltis: 1882-1952, 1952 Jan. 2; Pr. Ms Cy, 2p.; Dunn, L. C., (Leslie Clarence), 1893-1974 (Box 1)
    Published in Science 117 (1953): 3-4.
    Biographical and personal data -- Iltis, Hugo; Publication -- Science
  - to Arthur Koestler, 1972 Aug. 30; TLsS Cy, 4p.; Iltis, Hugh H. (Hugh Hellmut) (Box 1)
    Re: Case of the Midwife Toad.
  - to Hugh H. Iltis, 1972 Sept. 9; TLsS Cy, 2p.; Koestler, Arthur (Box 1)
  - Ein Wiener Gelehrte, n.d.; Pr. Ms Cy, 1p.; Bernfeld, Anne (Box 1)
  - Verführung durch Experiment, n.d.; Pr. Ms Cy, 1p.; Hahn, Arnold (Box 1)
  - Curriculum vitae, n.d.; TMs, 1p.; Iltis, Hugo (Box 1)
  - List of publications, n.d.; TMs, 3p.; Iltis, Hugo (Box 1)
    Bibliographical matters
  - Das biologische Zeitalter: Fortschritte der organischen Technik, n.d.; Pr. Ms, 20p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
  - Wilhelm Bülsche zum sechsigsten Geburtstag, n.d.; Pr. Ms, 3p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
  - Naturgeschichte des Strassenkämpfe, n.d.; Pr. Ms, 4p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
  - Organischen und soziale Technik, Pr. Ms, 2p.; Kammerer, Paul, 1880-1926 (Box 1)